Ed Begley Papers
Ed Begley Papers
1943-1965
Begley, Ed,1901-1970.
6.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American character actor of stage, screen, radio and television. Files, letters, photographs, telegrams, news clippings, scripts for radio, film, television and theatre. Of particular interest are the scripts, which document more than twenty years (roughly the mid-1940s through the mid-1960s) of drama in four different media, and the news clippings which describe the career of the American actor through these years.
148839
Biographical History
Actor Ed Begley (1901-1970) was an American actor who performed on stage, screen, radio, and television. Born in Hartford, Connecticut on March 25, 1901, he attended St. Patrick's school in Hartford from 1907 to 1915. He made his stage debut at the age of nine at the Globe Theatre in Hartford in an amateur show. He has had roles in numerous well-known plays, including Joe Keller in All My Sons, Dad in All Summer Long, Matthew Harrison Brady in Inherit the Wind, W.O. Gant in Look Homeward, Angel, and Orrin Knox in Advise and Consent.
Begley's television and radio career includes over 1000 radio broadcasts and many guest spots on such television programs as Ben Casey, Route 66, Dr. Kildare, Burke's Law, and The Virginian.
His screen appearances include The Great Gatsby, Stars in My Crown, Twelve Angry Men, Sweet Bird of Youth, Odds Against Tomorrow, Sitting Pretty, and The Unsinkable Molly Brown.
Begley's performance as Matthew Harrison Brady in Inherit the Wind won him the Donaldson Award in 1955, and in 1962 he won an Academy Award for Best Supporting Actor for his performance in Sweet Bird of Youth. Begley was married three times; his son Ed Begley, Jr. is an actor and environmental advocate. He was a member of the Actor's Equity Association, American Federation of Television and Radio Artists, and the Screen Actors Guild, as well as two theatrical social clubs, The Lambs and The Masquers.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ed Begley Papers consist of two accessions which have not been integrated.
1964 accession
The 1964 accession consists of correspondence, scripts, and memorabilia.
Correspondence consists of seven letters. Scripts, by far the bulk of this accession, consist of movie (including Cain's Hundred, Deadline USA, Stars in My Crown, and The Unsinkable Molly Brown), television (Dr. Kildare, The Virginian, and others), and radio shows (Fibber McGee and Molly, Hallmark Playhouse, and more. Memorabilia contains photographs, clippings, and a copy of MAD magazine with a parody of Begley.
1966 accession
The 1966 accession consists of general files, published material, scripts, and miscellaneous material.
General files include art work, financial accounts, legal contracts, reviews of various productions, photographs, playbills, and telegrams. Published material contains magazine issues and news clippings relating to Begley's performances. Scripts encompasses television, radio, theatre, and film; notable scripts include the stage version of Inherit the Wind and the movie version of Twelve Angry Men. Miscellaneous material contains programs, awards, news clippings, drawings, and theatre posters.
Arrangement of the Collection
The 1964 and 1966 accessions have not been integrated. All material is in alphabetical order; scripts are subdivided by type and then alphbetical by title.
Related Material
The library holds videotapes of several of Begley's performances. Please refer to for a complete listing and locations of this material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Popular culture; Radio, television, film; Begley, Ed, 1901-1970 -- Archives.; Actors -- United States.; Acting.; Motion picture actors and actresses.; Motion picture plays.; Radio actors and actresses; Radio scripts.; Television actors and actresses.; Television scripts.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Playbills.; Programs (documents); Scripts (documents); Actors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ed Begley, 1964.
Inventory
- Correspondence (1964)
  - 6 incoming letters, 1 outgoing letter in verse (Box 1)
- Scripts (1964)
  - Movie scripts
    - Cain's Hundred, mimeograph copy (Box 1)
    - Dark City, mimeograph copy (Box 1)
    - Deadline USA
      - Script, mimeograph copy (Box 1)
      - Revised production cast and credits (Box 1)
    - Fine 110, mimeograph copy; 2 copies (Box 1)
    - It Happens Every Spring, mimeograph copy (Box 1)
    - Lone Star, mimeograph copy (Box 1)
    - Policemen Die Alone, mimeograph copy (Box 1)
    - Somewhere In The City, mimeograph copy (Box 1)
    - Stars In My Crown
      - Final version, mimeograph copy (Box 2)
      - Temporary version (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous section (Box 2)
      - Ad lib lines, mimeograph copy (Box 2)
    - The Corruptors, mimeograph copy (Box 2)
    - The Farmer's Daughter, mimeograph copy (Box 2)
    - The Invaders, mimeograph copy (Box 2)
    - The Unsinkable Molly Brown, mimeograph copy (Box 2)
    - The Sure Thing, mimeograph copy (Box 2)
    - This Is Dynamite, mimeograph copy (Box 2)
    - Tulsa, mimeograph copy (Box 3)
    - Wyoming Mail, mimeograph copy (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous sections (Box 3)
  - Television scripts
    - Doctor Kildare, mimeograph copy; 2 copies (Box 3)
    - Hang No Hats On Dreams, mimeograph copy (Box 3)
    - The Dick Powell Show, mimeograph copy (Box 3)
    - The Virginian, mimeograph copy (Box 3)
    - Ulysses S. Grant, mimeograph copy (Box 3)
  - Radio scripts
    - Ford radio commercial, mimeograph copy (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous sections (Box 3)
    - Fibber McGee and Molly, mimeograph copy (Box 3)
    - Hollywood In Person, typescript copy (Box 3)
    - The Hallmark Playhouse, mimeograph copy (Box 3)
    - The Line-Up, mimeograph copy (Box 3)
    - The Red Danube, mimeograph copy (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous scripts (Box 4)
- Memorabilia (1964)
  - Copy of MAD Magazine containing parody of Ed Begley (Box 4)
  - Photos
    - Ed Begley and family (Box 4)
    - from Middle Of The Night (Box 4)
    - from All My Sons (Box 4)
    - from Inherit The Wind (Box 4)
    - from Ulysses S. Grant (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, Ed Begley and others (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 4)
  - Playbill (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous magazines (Box 4)
  - Sweet Bird of Youth (Box 4)
- General files (1966)
  - Art work (Box 5)
  - Biography, Ed Begley (Box 5)
  - Dramatic readings (Box 5)
  - Financial accounts (Box 5)
  - Fragments (Box 5)
  - Legal contracts (Box 5)
  - Letters
    - Business (Box 5)
    - Handwritten (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Magazine reviews
    - of All My Sons (Box 5)
    - General (Box 5)
    - of Inherit the Wind (Box 5)
    - Patterns (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Notes (Box 5)
  - Photographs
    - Begley (Box 5)
    - General (Box 5)
  - Playbills (Box 5)
  - Telegrams, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Theatre programs, 5 folders (Box 5)
- Published material (1966)
  - Magazines
    - The Call Board (Box 6)
    - Radio Directors Guild Yearbook, 1947 (Box 6)
    - Radio Row (Box 6)
    - Television (Box 6)
    - Theatre Arts (Box 6)
    - The Travelers Beacon (Box 6)
    - Tune In (Box 6)
    - WTIC, Hartford, Connecticut (Box 6)
  - News clippings, 13 clippings (Box 6)
- Scripts (1966)
  - Television (Box 6)
  - Television, 20 folders (Box 7)
  - Television, 18 folders, 1 volume (Box 8)
  - Radio, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Theatre
    - General (Box 9)
    - All My Sons (Box 9)
    - All Summer Long (Box 9)
    - Inherit the Wind, 2 volumes (Box 9)
    - Look Homeward Angel (Box 9)
    - A Shadow of My Enemy (Box 9)
  - Film
    - Ballad Number One (Box 9)
    - The Bitch Goddess Success (Box 9)
    - Deep Water, 2 volumes (Box 9)
    - Make It Fifty Dollars and Add Love to Nona (Box 9)
    - Odds Against Tomorrow, 2 volumes (Box 9)
    - Sitting Pretty (Box 9)
    - The Street With No Name, 2 volumes (Box 9)
    - The Street With No Name, 2 volumes (Box 10)
    - Twelve Angry Men (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous (1966)
  - Awards, 3 certificates, 1 rolled up in tube (Oversize 1)
  - Programs (Oversize 1)
  - News clippings (Oversize 1)
  - Drawings (Oversize 1)
  - Theatre posters (Oversize 1)